I'm a professional troublemaker.
我是个专业的麻烦制造者。
(Laughter)
(笑声)
As my job is to critique the world,
因为我的工作就是批判世界，
the shoddy systems and the people who refuse to do better,
批判劣质的系统与不求上进的人，
as a writer, as a speaker, as a shady Nigerian --
作为一名作家、演讲家 以及一名“臭名昭著”的尼日利亚人——
(Laughter)
（笑声）
I feel like my purpose is to be this cat.
我觉得我的工作 就和图中这只猫差不多。
(Laughter)
（笑声） （图片：自认清高的艺术家）
I am the person who is looking at other people,
我就是那种挑剔别人生活的人，
like, "I need you to fix it."
总想着 “我需要你改一改。”
That is me.
这就是我。
I want us to leave this world better than we found it.
我希望我们可以 让这个世界变得更好。
And how I choose to effect change
我选择改变世界的方式
is by speaking up,
是畅所欲言，
by being the first and by being the domino.
通过当第一张多米诺骨牌。
For a line of dominoes to fall,
为了让一排骨牌倒下，
one has to fall first,
必须有一个先倒下，
which then leaves the other choiceless to do the same.
剩下的骨牌别无选择， 就会跟着倒下。
And that domino that falls,
有了那张倒下的骨牌，
we're hoping that, OK,
我们希望
the next person that sees this is inspired to be a domino.
下个看到这个情况的人会被激励， 也成为一张骨牌。
Being the domino, for me, looks like speaking up
对我而言，作为骨牌就要公开表态，
and doing the things that are really difficult,
就要迎难而上，
especially when they are needed,
特别是当人们需要 有人挺身而出的时候，
with the hope that others will follow suit.
希望其他人也能效仿。
And here's the thing: I'm the person who says
此外还有一点： 我就是那种会说出
what you might be thinking but dared not to say.
想说但不敢说的话的人。
A lot of times people think that we're fearless,
人们经常会觉得 我们这种人是无所畏惧的，
the people who do this, we're fearless.
做这种事的人是无所畏惧的。
We're not fearless.
我们并不是无所畏惧。
We're not unafraid of the consequences
我们并不是不怕这些后果，
or the sacrifices that we have to make
也不是不惧怕
by speaking truth to power.
宣扬真理后的牺牲。
What happens is, we feel like we have to,
事实上，我们觉得这是我们的义务，
because there are too few people in the world
因为在这个世界
willing to be the domino,
愿意当骨牌的人太少，
too few people willing to take that fall.
鲜有人愿意第一个倒下。
We're not doing it without fear.
我们这么做不是不会恐惧。
Now, let's talk about fear.
现在，我们讲一讲恐惧。
I knew exactly what I wanted to be when I grew up.
我曾经很清楚长大后想做什么，
I was like, "I'm going to be a doctor!"
“我要成为一位医生!”
Doctor Luvvie was the dream.
当上医生是我曾经的梦想，
I was Doc McStuffins before it was a thing.
在《小医师大玩偶》流行起来之前 我就在扮演医师。
(Laughter)
（笑声）
And I remember when I went to college,
我记得我上大学的时候，
my freshman year, I had to take Chemistry 101
我大一的时候， 必须上化学基础这门课，
for my premed major.
为了我的预科主修做准备。
I got the first and last D of my academic career.
我拿了学术生涯中唯一的一个D。
(Laughter)
（笑声）
So I went to my advisor, and I was like,
于是我去找学校辅导员说：
"OK, let's drop the premed,
“我放弃医学院预科了，
because this doctor thing is not going to work,
因为我不是当医生的料，
because I don't even like hospitals.
因为我根本就不喜欢医院。
So ..."
所以...“
(Laughter)
（笑声）
"Let's just consider that done for."
“还是算了吧。”
And that same semester, I started blogging.
也是在那个学期，我开始写博客。
That was 2003.
那是2003年。
So as that one dream was ending, another was beginning.
当一个梦想结束的时候， 另外一个梦想开始了。
And then what was a cute hobby became my full-time job
后来，当我2010年失去了 市场营销工作的时候，
when I lost my marketing job in 2010.
这个可爱的爱好 就成为了我全职的工作。
But it still took me two more years to say, "I'm a writer."
但我花了两年多时间才能说： “我是个作家。”
Nine years after I had started writing, before I said, "I'm a writer,"
在我写作了九年之后我才说， “我是个作家。“
because I was afraid of what happens
因为我害怕
without 401ks,
没有退休金的后果，
without, "How am I going to keep up my shoe habit?
我害怕我不能 继续保持买鞋的习惯，
That's important to me."
那对我很重要。
(Laughter)
（笑声）
So it took me that long to own this thing
所以我需要花很长的时间
that was what my purpose was.
去了解我的目的是什么。
And then I realized,
然后我意识到，
fear has a very concrete power
恐惧是一股非常具体的力量，
of keeping us from doing and saying the things that are our purpose.
会阻止我们说出和践行 我们真正的目的。
And I was like, "You know what?
于是我想，“你知道吗？
I'm not going to let fear rule my life.
我不会让恐惧主宰我的生活。
I'm not going to let fear dictate what I do."
我不会让恐惧支配我的所作所为。”
And then all of these awesome things started happening,
于是所有奇妙的事情开始发生了，
and dominoes started to fall.
骨牌开始倒下了。
So when I realized that, I was like, "OK, 2015,
当我意识到的时候， 我开始想，“好，2015年
I turned 30,
我30岁了，
it's going to be my year of 'Do it anyway.'
这将是我 ‘不顾一切‘ 的一年
Anything that scares me, I'm going to actively pursue it."
我会积极地去追求 任何令我恐惧的事情。”
So, I'm a Capricorn.
我是个摩羯座，
I like my feel solidly on the ground.
我喜欢脚踏实地的感觉。
I decided to take my first-ever solo vacation,
我决定开启人生的首次个人旅行，
and it was out of the country to the Dominican Republic.
我决定去多米尼加共和国。
So on my birthday, what did I do?
那么在我生日的那一天， 我做了什么？
I went ziplining through the forests of Punta Cana.
我通过索道 穿越蓬塔·卡纳森林。
And for some odd reason, I had on business casual.
因为某些奇怪的原因， 我穿了商务装。
Don't ask why.
不要问我为什么。
(Laughter)
（笑声）
And I had an incredible time.
我度过了特别棒的时光。
Also, I don't like being submerged in water.
我不喜欢潜水。
I like to be, again, on solid ground.
再说一次， 我喜欢脚踏实地。
So I went to Mexico and swam with dolphins underwater.
所以我去了墨西哥， 在水下和海豚游泳。
And then the cool thing that I did also that year
那一年，我还做了一件超酷的事情，
that was my mountain
那是我的人生巅峰——
was I wrote my book,
我写了一本书，
"I'm Judging You: The Do-Better Manual,"
《我在评判你：如何做得更好》
And I had to own --
所以我现在应该算——
(Applause)
（掌声）
that whole writing thing now, right?
掌握写作的能力了，对吧？
Yes.
是的。
But the very anti-me thing that I did that year
但在那一年，我做的 最非常“反我”的事情，
that scared the crap out of me --
简直要吓死我了——
I went skydiving.
我去跳伞了。
We're about to fall out of the plane.
我们正要从飞机里跳下去的时候,
I was like, "I've done some stupid things in life. This is one of them."
我在想， “这绝对是我这辈子做过的蠢事之一。”
(Laughter)
（笑）
And then we come falling down to Earth,
接下来我们就向地面坠落，
and I literally lose my breath as I see Earth, and I was like,
我看着地面， 我简直无法呼吸，
"I just fell out of a perfectly good plane on purpose."
我在想，“我刚刚故意从一架 完好无损的飞机上跳下来了！”
(Laughter)
（笑）
"What is wrong with me?!"
“我有毛病吗？！”
But then I looked down at the beauty,
但当我俯视地表美景时，
and I was like, "This is the best thing I could have done.
我在想， ‘“这是我做过的最好的事情，
This was an amazing decision."
这是一个超棒的决定。”
And I think about the times when I have to speak truth.
我回想起需要 说出实话的那些时刻。
It feels like I am falling out of that plane.
那感觉就像正从飞机上掉下来，
It feels like that moment when I'm at the edge of the plane,
就像我在飞机边缘的那一刻，
and I'm like, "You shouldn't do this,"
我告诉自己，“你不应该这么做，”
but then I do it anyway, because I realize I have to.
但无论如何我还是做了， 因为我意识到自己必须去做。
Sitting at the edge of that plane
对我来说，坐在飞机边缘，
and kind of staying on that plane is comfort to me.
或者说呆在飞机上是很舒服的。
And I feel like every day that I'm speaking truth
我感觉，在我诉说真相，
against institutions and people who are bigger than me
和那些比我强大的机构和人，
and just forces that are more powerful than me,
以及那些更强大的势力抗衡的每一天。
I feel like I'm falling out of that plane.
都仿佛从那架飞机上掉下来一般。
But I realize comfort is overrated.
但我意识到， 舒适感其实被高估了。
Because being quiet is comfortable.
因为沉默是最舒适的。
Keeping things the way they've been is comfortable.
不去改变才是舒适的。
And all comfort has done is maintain the status quo.
但是舒适感能带给我们的 只有维护现状而已。
So we've got to get comfortable with being uncomfortable
所以我们应该通过 在必要的时候说出严峻的现实
by speaking these hard truths when they're necessary.
来学会走出自己的舒适区。
And I --
而且我——
(Applause)
（掌声）
And for me, though, I realize that I have to speak these truths,
我也意识到了坦白真相的重要性，
because honesty is so important to me.
因为诚实对于我来说非常重要。
My integrity is something I hold dear.
我珍惜我的正直。
Justice -- I don't think justice should be an option.
正义—— 我不认为正义是一个选项。
We should always have justice.
我们需要一直保持公平正义。
Also, I believe in shea butter as a core value, and --
不过，我相信 乳木果油也十分重要——
(Laughter)
（笑声）
and I think the world would be better if we were more moisturized.
因为如果我们更加滋润， 世界就会变得更好。
But besides that, with these as my core values,
但除此之外，
I have to speak the truth.
我的核心价值观是： 我必须讲出事实。
I have no other choice in the matter.
在这个问题上我没有其他的选择。
But people like me, the professional troublemakers,
但像我这样的人， 专业的麻烦制造者，
should not be the only ones who are committed to being these dominoes
不应该只有我们为成为骨牌献身，
who are always falling out of planes
不应该只有我们 总是从飞机上跳下来，
or being the first one to take this hit.
不应该只有我们成为靶子。
People are so afraid of these acute consequences,
人们惧怕严重的后果，
not realizing that there are many times when we walk in rooms
所以没有意识到，很多时候， 当我们走进房间时，
and we are some of the most powerful people in those rooms --
我们是房间里最强大的一批人——
we might be the second-most powerful, third-most powerful.
或者可能是第二强大、 第三强大的人。
And I firmly believe that our job in those times
并且我坚信那时我们的任务
is to disrupt what is happening.
是去中止正在发生的事。
And then if we're not the most powerful,
如果我们不是最强大的人，
if two more of us band together,
只要有更多的人加入我们，
it makes us powerful.
我们就会变得更强大。
It's like cosigning the woman in the meeting,
比如在开会时联合所有女性，
you know, the woman who can't seem to get her word out,
我们要让那些不敢发声的女性，
or just making sure that other person who can't make a point
那些不敢发表看法的人
is being heard.
能被倾听。
Our job is to make sure they have room for that.
我们的任务是为了 确保她们的这一权益。
Everyone's well-being is community business.
社会的目标就是确保每个人的幸福。
If we made that a point, we'd understand that,
如果我们明确了这一点， 我们就会了解到，
for the times when we need help,
当我们需要帮助的时候，
we wouldn't have to look around so hard
如果我们曾经对他人施以援手，
if we made sure we were somebody else's help.
就不必艰难地四处求助。
And there are times when I feel like
有时候，我在公共场合
I have taken very public tumbles and falls,
会感到十分受挫，
like the time when I was asked to speak at a conference,
比如有一次， 我受邀去会议上发表演讲，
and they wanted me to pay my way there.
他们想让我自付差旅费。
And then I did some research
然后我做了些调查，
and found out the white men who spoke there got compensated
发现在那儿演讲的 白人男性都拿到了酬劳，
and got their travel paid for.
并报销了他们的差旅费。
The white women who spoke there got their travel paid for.
在那儿演讲的白人女性 至少也拿到了差旅费。
The black women who spoke there were expected to actually pay to speak there.
而黑人女性，却需要自费演讲。
And I was like, "What do I do?"
我就在想，“我该怎么办？“
And I knew that if I spoke up about this publicly,
我知道如果将这件事公之于众，
I could face financial loss.
我可能会面对财务损失。
But then I also understood that my silence serves no one.
但是我也知道 我的沉默不会帮助任何人。
So I fearfully spoke up about it publicly,
所以尽管心中十分忐忑， 我还是公开地谈论了这件事情。
and other women started coming out to talk about,
之后其他女性也开始站出来谈论，
"I, too, have faced this type of pay inequality."
“我也面对过这种不公平的待遇。”
And it started a conversation about discriminatory pay practices
于是我们开始讨论那个会议的
that this conference was participating in.
歧视性报酬。
I felt like I was the domino
当我读到一位公众人物
the time I read a disturbing memoir by a public figure
带有歧视性的回忆录 并写了一些读后感时，
and wrote a piece about it.
我觉得我成了一张骨牌，
I knew this person was more powerful than me and could impact my career,
我知道这个人比我更强大， 他可能会影响我的事业，
but I was like, "I've got to do this.
但我想，“我得做这件事。
I've got to sit at the edge of this plane," maybe for two hours.
我得坐在“飞机”的边缘， 想了大概两个小时，
And I did. And I pressed "Publish," and I ran away.
最后决定放手一搏。 我按了“发布”键，然后溜了。
(Laughter)
（笑声）
And I came back to a viral post
然后我发现这篇文章 收到了极高的关注，
and people being like, "Oh my God, I'm so glad somebody finally said this."
人们在说，“天哪，我很开心 终于有个人说这个了。“
And it started a conversation
然后它开启了一场
about mental health and self-care,
关于精神健康和自我照顾的讨论，
and I was like, "OK. Alright.
我想，“好啊，
This thing that I'm doing, I guess, alright, it's doing something."
我猜我正在做的这件事情， 正在产生影响。”
And then so many people have been the domino
然后当很多人开始讨论
when they talk about how they've been assaulted by powerful men.
自己怎么被位高权重的男性 抨击的时候，他们也成为了骨牌。
And it's made millions of women join in and say, "Me Too."
然后数百万女性也加入进来， 并说出，“我也是。”
So, a shout-out to Tarana Burke for igniting that movement.
在此，要感谢 塔拉娜·伯克点燃了这场运动。
(Applause)
（掌声）
People and systems count on our silence to keep us exactly where we are.
大众和体制在依靠 我们的沉默去维持现状。
Now, being the domino sometimes comes down to being exactly who you are.
但有的时候成为骨牌就是在做自己。
So, I've been a shady somebody since I was three.
我从三岁起就是个 名声不怎么样的人。
(Laughter)
（笑声）
This is me on my third birthday.
这是我三岁生日时的照片。
But I've been this girl all my life,
但我这一生从未改变，
and I feel like even that's been the domino,
我始终觉得应该去当那一张骨牌，
because in a world that wants us to walk around
因为上帝想让我们去
as representatives of ourselves,
为自己发声，
being yourself can be a revolutionary act.
活出自我是一种革命性的行为。
And in a world that wants us to whisper,
在一个想让我们谨言慎行的世界里，
I choose to yell.
我选择大声呼喊。
(Applause)
（掌声）
When it's time to say these hard things,
当我感到有些事情 让我难以启齿的时候，
I ask myself three things.
我会问自己三个问题，
One: Did you mean it?
第一：你是认真的吗？
Two: Can you defend it?
第二：你可以为它辩护吗？
Three: Did you say it with love?
第三：你是为爱发声吗？
If the answer is yes to all three,
如果这三个问题的答案都是肯定的，
I say it and let the chips fall.
我就会不计后果地说出来。
That's important.
那很重要。
That checkpoint with myself
这三个问题
always tells me, "Yes, you're supposed to do this."
始终给予我肯定的力量。
Telling the truth -- telling thoughtful truths --
说实话—— 说出深思熟虑的实话——
should not be a revolutionary act.
不应该成为革命性的举动。
Speaking truths to power should not be sacrificial, but they are.
对权势说真话不应该 意味着牺牲，但事实却是如此。
But I think if more of us chose to do this for the greater good,
但是如果更多的人能加入我们，
we'd be in better spaces than we are right now.
我们的处境会比现在更好。
Speaking of the greater good,
说到更好的世界，
I think we commit ourselves to telling truths to build bridges
我认为我们有责任 用真相搭建桥梁，
to common ground,
去连接共同点，
and bridges that aren't based on truth will collapse.
那些没有用真相 搭建起来的桥梁就会崩塌。
So it is our job,
所以，这是我们的工作，
it is our obligation, it is our duty
我们的义务和责任
to speak truth to power, to be the domino,
不屈从于权贵，去成为骨牌，
not just when it's difficult --
不只是在艰难的时候——
especially when it's difficult.
尤其是在艰难的时候。
Thank you.
谢谢。
(Applause)
（掌声）